welcome everyone
after a brief hiatus we are back with
another awakening for the meaning crisis
discord q
a we are here with brent cooper who is
the
executive director of the app of
abstract.org welcome brent thank you for
being here today
thank you my pleasure so
brett you had a really interesting
voices with for vicky
about a month and a half ago with john
and
you the topic was metamodernism
and you went over you know a bunch of
concepts that i think
uh we'd like to to get into a bed and
get
maybe some some lay clarification for
the
for the uh for the for the less
academically uh
uh inclined uh in our audience
now but but first could you just give us
a brief tour of your your history
you know what what brought you here
what's
your work about how did you meet john
how does your work intersect with john
sure um my background is in sociology
and
international relations going back about
a decade ago to when i
left the university system
um and i was interested in this idea of
metamodernism since then
because i was very prone to meta
perspectives through the
meta theory that i was working on and
through
the sort of cultural turn we're in and
my own experiences with psychedelics and
stuff like that
and just a lifelong passion for
philosophy so
there's all those intersections and i
kind of see myself as
art sociologist part artist because i've
made a
made a film about abstraction about
philosophy
which is a satire in which i encouraged
john to watch
to understand the whole breadth of my
project
and i've written a lot sort of
non-fiction about
abstraction as a philosophy as a
practice
as a critique of society um
as a critique of capital in fact um
and i you know have crossed paths with
john in
several spaces we were both in the side
view together
and he had come into hanzi frank's
mailing list before that
and of course i've seen some of his
other content and i think a lot of
different circles
are different adjacent spaces overlap
like one is you know has a
relationship with people like jordan
hall but
john himself isn't too involved with the
game b
discourse which i've criticized and so
there's these
and i've you know participated in so
um yeah we're all neighbors in this
sense and i i reached out to john to
kind of pursue some more concrete
engagement and
lightly start to challenge him and
uh you know i requested him to help me
too to sort of unpack a lot of my ideas
because
i do a lot more writing than speaking
with a chance to
have a a dialogue with people
is uh is a practice to explore that
right
so that that's what brought me here too
great and so so for everyone who who's
here now i i've
posted a link to your uh side view
article uh just up in in event text so
if you just scroll up a bit
there's a link to your your first voices
with forever you understand you've had
you've recorded a second one yet but
it's not up
not yet up on the site so maybe we can
have you back
back another time uh to discuss that one
uh
but uh so so no it's interesting what
what what you just seemed to say was
that you're
you're you're critic you were talking
with john uh
sort of coming across from a more
critical perspective are there
areas of what areas of john's work do
you are you critical of
um there like to be clear
very very little in the specific content
of his work
but it's it's partly that i wanted to
share with him kind of a meta critique
of what's going on
in these conversation spaces right so
john has
done a lot of that with game b people
with the rebel wisdom community
and those communities have excluded me
and i think they are they're far from
perfect right
they're they need critical perspectives
and even if they say that they
entertain them uh you know quite often
they're
talking out of the side of their mouth
and if i did have a critique of
verveiki's work
it would you know it would take me a
while to formulate obviously i'd have to
consume all his 50 videos and you know
be versed in the literature that he is
and just be very serious about it
but my general critique that
you know i agreed to i agreed with john
not to have those conversations on the
record
but i'm critical of a lot of people for
politics for political reasons and for
political discourse so
i'm trying to elicit and manifest
more mature conversations about politics
which
some of these adjacent spaces like game
b like integral like the stoa
um the emerge network which i'm a part
of
they eschew taking strong political
positions
uh for one reason or another and it's
you know it's a very tricky thing to do
but i'm trying to uh
foster those conversations so those are
some deeper conversations that i'd like
to
have with john the second conversation
we recorded
uh stayed stayed true to the point we
closed on
in our first conversation which was
metanoia
you know we both have an interest in
that topic
so that's that was our jumping off point
in the second interview which we
recorded which hasn't been posted yet
so i know in in your talk with your
first talk with john
you you said you like to go against the
grain
and you're attracted to radical politics
what kind of radical politics do are you
attracted to
sure i mean it's um
it's very becoming more normalized and
mainstream
these days because if you take the
movements of socialism for example
especially in the united states has been
very marginalized throughout its history
like europe despite what it's been
through has been able to have more
mature conversations about socialism and
about the welfare state and healthcare
and things like this the united states
has not because for a
variety of reasons but it's essentially
a failed state
and issuing politics is not the way to
solve that
my radical politics is very basic very
universal very unobjectional you know
environmentalism taking care of people
through universal healthcare and
education
demilitarization ending the war on drugs
no green new deal things like this i
think are pretty non-controversial
but pretty much everything gets
politicized
in in public discourse in media of
course and that's
no secret everybody who's
oh you know remotely attuned
is aware of that nevertheless people
still you know kind of follow their
tribes and
argue aggressively for different
contrarian points of view
and i'm trying to just
help normalize and establish a healthier
discourse around
say democratic socialism and
so it's a long-term radicalism you know
i don't i don't uh
don't endorse eco-terrorism or anything
like that
violence but as a sociologist we have to
understand
violence and social movements
through serious lenses you know we we
can't just
write off different things and we need
to take speech acts
and uh you know uh
political politicization of things as
also
act of violence in a way like white
white-collar crime
is much less prosecuted and much less
direct in its visible impacts it's a
very
ubiquitous thing and it's very harmful
it has
it has ripple effects and consequences
that do
cause violence it's it's it's entangled
with things like the
military-industrial complex so we need
to be serious about how
we think critically about where violence
originates from
and and how we actually reduce it you
know
thinking about comparisons between
riders for example in a a police state
it uses authorized lethal force against
people
often with very little discretion and i
think you know the bernie sanders
movement
two years in a row it's been very
straightforward very populist
great grassroots detracted
huge bases of people and if it weren't
for the obstruction
of establishment forces you know
media conglomerates and and different
intellectual spaces
everywhere from the new york times to
these little
niche you know innovation spaces
they obstructed that that mass movement
and without good reasons then they're
contributing to this
sort of crisis not just the meaning
crisis but the actual
tangible material crisis uh that we face
as a as a planet
oh so you know given my background
to foreground politics and i've
encountered a lot of resistance and a
lot of suppression
just trying to to get basic points
across and of course
there's it's well documented like the
phenomenon of the bernie blackout for
example
again i say if it weren't for those
kinds of forces and
the like
lack of lack of like broader convergence
towards those ends um i i think we'd be
on the right track historically speaking
you know now we're in a
um a very nihilistic situation
where the american voters have to choose
between joe biden and donald trump
and so my critique to john you know
privately mostly and
and sort of to everyone publicly is that
uh
if you didn't speak up you helped enable
this i i lost count of the amount of
people whether they're just trolls or
very so-called serious thinkers
who laugh at the idea that this is
fascism
serious political science view and in
sociological and historical view
is that that what trump represents what
the republican party represents and what
aspects of the democratic
democratic party represent are aspects
of neo-fascism
and neo-feudalism so
i i'm pushing a serious conversation
about that but
when i meet someone like john i have to
start with it's
of closer convergence like metaphor
the meeting crisis metanoia and
metamodernism broadly and so
uh through that continued engagement we
can sort of
shape each other's understanding um
and uh yeah that's that's where i'm
going with this
yeah so so it's interesting i so i i
would probably
i class would classify myself more as a
social democrat
uh so i'm probably more on the
wishy-washy
liberal side i think that you better i
see you right about you know i'm center
left you know i'm canadian i like
i like okay i like you so a liberal oh i
okay yeah i i
you know i'm i i'm probably in favor of
you know capitalism
per se but i like i like a strong uh
social
safety net you know i like universal
health care and uh welfare state and you
know to fill in the gaps
but so i i sort of i lean towards john's
view as well
that that for example this movement here
you know that we're
sort of in here the awakening from the
meeting crisis shouldn't be
necessarily actively political that
being said
where i'm very with you it is
that we should be able to have these
conversations
with one another in a respectful manner
that that
far leftists and far rightists and
everybody in between
should be able to talk to one another
and you know to have sort of
like a dialogue style approach to having
these conversations without
calling each other evil without thinking
of each other as evil i mean most of the
time
you know it's i think it's people
wanting to do good seeking good but
having widely divergent ways of getting
there
and seeing you know we have our natural
tribal biases that lead us to see the
other
as as as evil as as
nefarious and up up to no good so so
certainly
i i think that we should be
finding venues and to have the you know
some
you know somber you know polite
civil discourse between these widely
uh divergent views and i think that
might lead us to better understand one
another
and see each other less as nefarious and
maybe
we can then find the areas that we agree
with one another
and and focus there
yeah so
so yeah okay so yes go ahead
well i wasn't sure if you were done you
want me to riff refund that or
sure yeah um
i'm all for it um
one of the things i you know i looked up
the video
uh with me and john on youtube just to
i didn't watch it but i was like just
checking out what was there when it was
posted
and i noticed the title he went with it
was like meta modernism in the idw
i don't remember talking too much about
that
maybe we touched on it but it is
something that i foreground in my work
and the you know the the premise and the
pretense
of the intellectual dark web is that
they were doing exactly that that they
were having difficult
civil conversations and that we're
actually breaking ground in some
regard i understand this movement very
well because i understand where it came
from
you know i was sort of part of the
emergence of new atheism in the late
2010s and i i completely understand that
that that uh western civilization and
kind of
rationality and reason-based
movement and i understand what it's
evolved into and
i've i've become more politically
literate and savvy as
as time has gone on too so i feel like i
grew out of that before the
intellectual dark web emerged
and oh i've done i've tracked it i've
done the research
i've tried to participate in some of
those discourses
and it seems to me very clearly
antithetical to its
stated you know values and
you know and a number of individuals
immediately come to mind and so
as well as some of the more peripheral
ones but um
you know it does not meet my criteria
for serious
intellectual discussion and much less
for
political commentary and and though they
try to be kind of de-politicized
it's very political and
so that's a major point of frustration
or me and for many people
just to just to see that movement uh
thrive and then kind of mutate and
you know where we are today the
intellectual dark web doesn't exactly
exist in its previous form it's
fragmented and and changed but it's
still very problematic in my opinion and
i'm still seeking to demonstrate what a
what a real
civil productive conversation looks like
and the most important thing
i think the key is to be able to take
valid
criticism take real critique into or to
critique yourself
anticipate and to process that and
you're not one of these
you know kind of just like blowhard
pundits or even if you're even if
they're very soft-spoken
you know they're just very opinionated
and they're very self-centered
and that that is not actually
uh breaking ground in any way if you if
you follow my logic
and so just very briefly case in point
is the weinstein brothers and what
they're doing with the kind of unity
and who they talk to and who they don't
talk to and how they talk about
the people that they don't talk to it's
extremely hypocritical
and it's an exhausting kind of side
project for me to kind of keep up with
the criticism of them
to you know deploy my own criticism
occasionally
and it's been it's been very fruitless
regardless of the approach and so
um you know i i hope i can sort of
win that little culture skirmish in one
way or another
uh pretty soon because it's going
nowhere fast
so what do you think is needed to
you know what i often see
gets in the way of sides getting
together is our internal bias our tribal
bias
and and this is unconscious you know we
we when we see of them we have this
instinctive sense of distrust this
cognitive dissonance this
and and that can really get in the way
and my thought is that
to to really open people up we have to
sort of control for our biases we have
to
get past our biases or around our biases
to to open people up you know just
saying i'm open-minded isn't really
isn't really enough what do you think is
needed to
open up these conversations to let these
people with widely divergent views get
past
their their instinctive just taste of
the other to have a civil discussion
yeah it's it's tricky but it's possible
the first thing that comes to mind is
mediation
you know get way more mediation and not
just any mediation we need much
much better protocols for mediation you
know the the
the times i've seen it done it's often
disappointing
and that's one thing
another is just a shift in attitudes
you know and so this idea of auto
critique
being able to you know spend spend much
of our
you know research and philosophical
energy
deconstructing your own assumptions you
know that that's part of
the process or the philosophy of
post-modernism writ large
which the intellectual dark web tried to
you know
debunk or steer around
and you know regardless of how it's
phrased and by who it's largely an
anti-academic movement and of course
academia has its own
problems but not for lack of
good you know like good research by
humanity scholars
as like noam chomsky says it's the
problem is actually the opposite
universities are not controlled by
left-wingers they're controlled by
right-wingers by
right-wing ideology and they've and in
fact they are but it's subtle
because universities have become very
corporatist and
pulled into financial structures into
neoliberal austerity and and things like
this so
so you know people who claim to be a
claim the mantle of public intellectual
should be able to
to to perceive what i'm saying be and a
lot's been
written about it you know so to
to enter into academic debates seriously
one has to be
already literate and engaged
and you know the the zizek versus
peterson debate for example
um whatever one may interpret from it
the fact
is that peterson is not read into
marxist literature which is a
cornerstone
of sociology there's no there's no two
ways about it
and so and that's kind of an admission
on his part it's it kind of turned the
tide in public opinion about him
but um it also you know sort of helped
uh continue to complete his transition
to the to
the right wing completely
so you know this is this is a lot of
damage that has to be
undone intellectually and and john is
uh someone who you know worked
very close to peterson and has his own
critiques of peterson
and so it's good that he does and he can
approach it in his own
way and i'll choose choose how he frames
it and how he deals with peterson
personally i don't have that uh sort of
luxury right and so but i respect the
fact that he has a critique i think
that's that's important
it's important for us to sort of stand
up to each other and confront each other
of course you know john finds out like
many people
that peterson doesn't take critique
while it doesn't uh it's not it's not
fruitful and it puts us in kind of a
paradox
and so that that returns to your
question you know how
how do we actually do it
and um you know
just reaching across the aisle and
having conversations with different
people
isn't enough in itself all the time
you know it as i said at the beginning
with having a mediator
it needs to be purposefully structured
to be good faith
right like i watched an interview once
of uh ezra klein and ben shapiro
it's it's it's garbage it's not
productive
it doesn't have any uh conversion
ratio it doesn't have any impact except
to you know get some clicks and
so it's very disappointing in that
regard and and you can see
watching it that there is no mediation
of course neither of them are properly
briefed in any sort of common ground
and it's just a wasted opportunity so
i'm not saying don't
talk to ben shapiro but stop
wasting opportunities and that that's my
critique of everybody you know
box is kind of part of
you know the the the the left-leaning
center if you will
and it's it's i think it it has some
value and some reach
but is uh also
kind of kind of confused about
the broader reality of someone like a
ben shapiro
right and if you look at the the lengthy
list of left critiques of ben shapiro
they're they're they're cutting they're
ruthless they're funny
they're accurate and and there are
they're everything they need to be up to
and including you know debates
with people on the far right and a lot
of that stuff doesn't get
doesn't get um play in these other
intellectual spaces
for one reason or another like it's hard
to keep track with all those
different different happenings in
different spaces i think it's all
relevant and if we could
you know build consensus sooner and
faster
oh people masses of people
it would would um be saved the time
going down
endless rabbit holes and and you know
youtube's algorithm which draws people
to the right
and et cetera et cetera so
a lot of this could have been avoided if
a more inclusive space was created in
the first place that included
like proper leftists right from
from the kind of legacy of gnome chomsky
down
you know to young socialists like owen
jones and
uh nathan robinson you know their their
voices just aren't
aren't heard because people associate
they have different connotations of the
of the word socialism
right and you know
smart people wouldn't pursue these
policies if there wasn't
a legitimate critical foundation to them
and public support for them
so part of my background is in the
sociology of knowledge
and so what i'd like to do and it's very
difficult to do this is kind of keep
mapping out
the the contours of different discourses
and
demonstrate how knowledge is is created
and produced and disseminated and
how it's internalized with us
so we can have a better epistemology
better ways ways of knowing better ways
of trusting
the right sources of knowledge and
uh so we can be more confident in in
gaining political power and asserting
universal policies
through uh left-wing politics like as
you said you're we're both canadian so
like the ndp
for example so you know that's that's a
conversation
that that has to be had i try to have
those conversations with my
family it's very difficult to try to
have them online
very difficult and i don't even
particularly
enjoy being political um it's just
it it comes from my sociology
and so that's a whole another level of
conversation that's not
typically being had and
so you know through my work i've tried
to
a lot of different sources together
and and uh engage with somebody like
john to kind of prevent
uh present uh such such a synthesis
and alternative and keep moving us
forward
let just one more point on that whole
kind of rant
oh donald trump says in the debate last
night that like critical
race theory is racist this is a trope
that people like jordan peterson have
been thrown around for several years and
so it's in the mainstream consciousness
and it's essentially trumpian in its
nature
but a lot of smart people have come to
believe this
and i i insist it's kind of a brain worm
because
none of those people can define critical
race theory
adequately i i challenge any of them to
do it it's actually
that idea just like modernism and
post-modernism these ideas are quite
irreducible
i have a lot of depth and complexity in
the academic literature
and we can't just throw them around in a
completely
orwellian sense like saying critical
race theory itself is racist when
there's other
systemic racist problems in the united
states and globally so
this should be obvious but it's but it's
not
there are a lot of threads we could pick
up there we have a couple questions uh
from from from our members so christian
d
uh says brent what do you think about
fixing the information ecology
because not everyone sees the conception
of progressive left that you are
embodying
good question um
uh that's a good question there's two
questions there one is what do we do
about
the information ecology and the other is
what do we do about
the kind of definition of progressive
left
are they're both good questions so the
first
you know i i i try to you know clean my
own
information ecology and i try to
i try to promote that
idea for you know for better or worse
it's a very real issue think of it it's
best to think of it in terms of
diet right like intellectual diet what
kind of books do you consume
right being in a community like
verveiki's
it's very academic obviously he's
telling you to go read
you know
heidegger or corbin or whoever
you know by all means do it you increase
your your
breath of understanding but it's
very difficult to interpret that kind of
philosophy politically sometimes and
it's very difficult
to parse political information
at all in general i've been very
cynical and skeptical about politics for
most of my life
until a i studied it formally and
started to understand
how things work both you know both in
terms of the the performance of politics
and the
and the mechanisms of governance
um
oh [ __ ] where is it going
i i totally forgot those choosing your
sources and
yeah um you know
you know i i politics is is very
difficult and so oh yeah
what i was going to say was basically
you know i was cynical and skeptical
you know through through the clinton
years through the bush years through the
obama years
um because that's just that that was my
innate perspective you know i loved
comedy i loved
criticism you know but like you know
just like george carlin or like a
musician like frank zappa who's very
political like these are radical
thinkers not just artists and and many
actual philosophers and stuff you know
and so it wasn't until
somebody like bernie sanders reached a
national level profile
and i found a movement to properly
believe in
because there's so many you know
characters in politics especially if
you're looking at the
macro level you know trying to know who
all the heads of state are and trying to
know at the local level
the different political and demographic
dynamics it's
it's also it's almost impossible to keep
up with it
so you have to know what commentators to
trust in different spaces
and you have to know what politicians to
trust right
and so it's typically the ones with a
smaller profile
who who are more genuine more kind of
career progressives take like ralph
nader
for example you know who who is like
blamed for the 2000 election but of
course it's
it's not his fault if you look at ralph
nader's career
oh he deserves a nobel peace prize more
than obama does
for if we're serious he doesn't have the
same profile the same reach look at mike
gravel
right who also ran for president this
year another lifelong
proper progressive right somebody like
joe biden if you look at his career
it's being a centrist democrat
though those are just the facts and
politics aside
one of the thing most of us increasingly
agree upon
in these kind of meta spaces is that
we're
we're in a deepening crisis
and that has been
in the making four decades for for for
at least 50 years you know and so
part of the awakening to the meaning
crisis
is and has to be an awakening to this
kind of oh kind of
this narrative which is a poor it has a
poor signal-to-noise ratio
that that most people layman
to be derogatory but just to say what
most people are kind of fed
through media and through through
consumerist narratives
it's um it's contributing to this sort
of death spiral
so information ecology you know we have
to be very critical
and progressive left we have to do a bit
of homework
we have to look at actual history we
have to spend the time
actually investing in uh
progressive media channels and there's a
slew of them
there's countless
you know and you know
um
oh so the the the question goes back to
you guys and the questioner it's like
what well where
where are you at in terms of your
information ecology and
when was the last time you you audited
or took a chance on a
a new a new channel or a new
path and um you know or what when's the
last time you you tried to
advocate for something like eliminating
homelessness or for advocating for a ubi
like
you to engage in that activity
to understand how difficult it is and
how much of the capitalist
sort of um path dependence
is is against that is against doing the
right thing
you know part of the awakening
has to be awareness to the the broad
fact that climate change has been
systematically suppressed for you know
between 70 and 100 years
and it's become excruciatingly clear
in the past sort of decade
process of denial and suppression works
and so it um you know i think it
overlaps with
a very
it overlaps with scientific narratives
it overlaps with um
conspiracy narratives and um we need to
start
believing in what's true in that regard
and it'll
act as an attractor and draw us towards
their conclusions and their
die logos one of john's key focuses now
is uh on rationality as one of the key
components being guarding against
self-deception
and we're currently going through the
wisdom of hypatia
and on his saturday uh
into saturday courses and a big
focus is wouldn't you know not focused
on
on picking the right media but but how
how we go about you know cultivating our
ability to
guard against self-deception and
which should apply to all areas you know
whether it's
medium arguing with people
and so on
yeah i suppose i have two kind of
answers to that
one is the process what you're looking
for
is to be very open-minded but very
skeptical you know
i'm i'm critical of an over-reliance on
the process
in the kind of fetishization of these
different processes
you know peter limberg calls himself a
performative agnostic and he's committed
to taking in as many
perspectives as possible
and um you know being an intellectual
explorer as he calls it
i think that's a phase that you go
through i think it's very important
you need to come out on the other side
of it with with moral convictions
and intellectual clarity
and and it should be grounded in in in
something
concrete it can't just be the process
has to be grounded in
in a source you know we have to know how
to um
if we can't trust ourselves we need to
know who who else to trust
and unfortunately so many people
you know you know they place their trust
in
in the wrong person or just somebody
as a placeholder because we don't know
um
and and so for me you know being
self-critical and self-auditing
it's not just contemplating that process
and doing it in reflection that's a big
part of it but
study you know what what i was trained
in
and what what i what i did in my
self-direct
directed studies through university you
know i pick
some of the most complex unanswered
questions
questions of power knowledge and secrecy
and
these things are on one hand very
well researched um on the other hand
very like diluted with different
conspiracy narratives
so i approached conspiracy
sort of as an academic that studies the
phenomenon
that allowed me to kind of reshape my
own understanding of
of power relations and complex events
um but then i studied
uh kind of several layers deeper of the
approach to that to that topic
right so like like sort of world history
is is very important in that regard
and there's a sense in which we're all
kind of
trapped in systems of control in
buckets of ignorance uh you know in the
conspiracy spectrum goes from very wacky
obviously
provably false ideas two
um very
well-known historical sort of
conspiracies whether they're corporate
conspiracies or
political ones they they certainly exist
and they and they
they've had major turning points in
world history
so things like jfk and 911 are perhaps
unsolvable
but things like the gulf of tonkin
incident or the
reichstag fire are well are proven
at this point their their public
knowledge that they were
sort of practical conspiracies and
my higher level analysis is about
how even beyond that
you know we're all we're all kind of um
sort of you know pawns in some sort of
evolutionary conspiracy
um which uh there's a source for that um
from a biologist and so
you know i'm sort of grounding these
academic insights
in um interdisciplinary sources
and these are some of the deepest
questions of meaning
so to speak so it always comes back to
that
you know and is relevant to to you guys
because we're all
searching for answers but there's
there's at the end of the day there's
very very simple and basic sociological
reasons
that were also ignorant even the smart
ones
you know we we kind of and this is this
explains
trump's rise to power you know it's not
sufficient to blame
white nationalists but to also blame
the you know the
um kind of compliance of the liberal
establishment
in in enabling that and so
i think it's important for us all to
admit
and to have sort of guilt and kind of
atonement and a sort of metanoia
moment to recognize that we've all made
mistakes
we've all had ideological moments we've
all grown up from
child a childhood of magical thinking
and and being lied to by different
adults and so this is something this is
unfinished
still there's there's not just a culture
war between right and left there's a
culture war between boomers and
millennials
and so these are unresolved and and
it just takes people to commit to
resolving it
to to begin the process like you know if
we show up and
they show up it can happen i
spoke with a i
on sunday who identifies as as meta
right
this is something i don't support at all
i'm willing because it's essentially
kind of race-based
but but i but i'm willing to talk to
them you know they're they're not going
to stop from appropriating different
discourses
and i'm willing to open up and
and have a have a candid vulnerable
encounter
and and also be clear about the terms
that like
you know we we have to defer authority
to different people when we don't quite
understand things
so this person thought he
you know had a had a pretty good
philosophy of history and
a pretty good grasp of
certain ideas and you certainly
good intentions and reading some left
sources
but but you know he he's all you know
he had no degrees and that in itself
shouldn't rule out somebody being
correct
it means he doesn't respect
um you know academics who
devote their lives to that kind of thing
and so with the internet we're all kind
of
armchair researchers and pundits
all of us who who do this kind of thing
and i'm not interested
in like a hierarchy in that regard
you know i'm i'm i'm in the trenches
with everybody else
but uh if we really believe that there's
some truth out there to
to grasp we have to do it together and
these these hyper nationalist
ethno-nationalist narratives are just
dead ends and they're completely at odds
with kind of a
cosmopolitan consensus that uh that
informs a lot of social science and
you know just to close out this little
this little thread too
one of my areas of research which i've
neglected because it needs more
resources to actually execute something
called public sociology
and there's just not a lot of kind of um
access to sociologists you know
things like think tanks and news
organizations are supposed to mediate
and a lot of you know podcasts and stuff
fill that gap and try to educate the
public
but um you know think tanks which you
think are a kind of
nexus of critical
collaboration are often part of the
problem
for one for one reason or another so
everything has to be audited
and the kind of broad
efforts of sociology need to be
uh translated and and uh deployed into
the public and of course that means mass
education is necessary
and one of one of the things i try to
frame this struggle in often is like the
20th century was largely about
psychology
making psychology public giving people
access to that
the whole self-help industry et cetera
and so on
now the 21st century demands
that we have a sociological imagination
and we're we're definitively in a
post-truth environment right where
conglom conglomerates constrict the flow
of information through the media
as do think tanks and people
ordinary people and pundits alike are
trafficking in a lot of
distractions and false narratives
so um you know i'm entering the fray and
uh also practicing the the
methods with you guys to try to unpack
some of that
you know i i just noticed that you know
some of
those we have people on this forum uh of
all different political stripes again we
don't talk too much about politics here
but
we have people who are more right people
are more left people who like trump
people who don't like trump
um but so so i notice for example
in your discourse here you know you
don't seem to like a lot of the people
on the right
uh and you use language that makes that
clear do you think that using
more so to speak diplomatic language can
make people more
open to hearing your message
and so so i think people on each side
have a tendency to villainize the other
and if we were more saw them not as
villains but as
people who maybe we think are misguided
but who
have different views but are probably
seeking the good
it lowers that sense of distrust between
people
uh that that leads to discussions
breaking down
sure it depends who it is you know
and i i have to practice be more
diplomatic when i'm
speaking to an audience that i don't
know but i'm also trying to be
authentic and confident in these in
these positions because i can defend
them
when i criticize the right it's it's
against people who
are known to be sort of frauds
or who don't engage in debate or
criticism
you know they're they're they're just
demonstrably
demagogues and it's
it's it's a sort of a paradox that
someone who's on the right would be
offended by that characterization like
if i say ben
shapiro's full of [ __ ] and you happen to
like ben shapiro
i still want to talk to you but um
that person is gonna is gonna is gonna
wince and think that we're incompatible
and that they that they know better than
me
um i think there's limits to compassion
i'm not saying don't use it but i'm
saying like
is it working because there's there's
different levels of forces
which co-opt the whole the whole game
you know i think the bernie movement by
and large did everything right
they weren't given a fair hearing in the
public sphere
and the right-wing right-wing people
were fed lies and so
part of what i'm trying to do is break
that false consciousness
you know whether you do that in an i
swear in a in a
in a direct way you know i don't know
but we have to commit
to to breaking that because i mean i i
encourage any conservative to name their
their favorite politician on the right
it's just
it's just a non-starter if we you know
and i'm not trying to
get into a kind of mudslinging contest
based on different conspiracy theories
of the
of the sides versus each other right
because there is different theories on
both sides right
and you know and there's more than
there's more than two sides it's a very
multi-polar or
kind of culture war but
but the but the people you know none of
us are impartial
right and and the people who claim to be
are i think doing it doing a disservice
uh to themselves and genuine people like
me
who want to follow through on some of
these problems and get and get clear
answers
and just to remind people if you have a
question you can post it
in the event text mark you have a
question
sure so um i i saw your talk with john
and i'm getting a feel for your idea
around
uh addressing politics directly and
so i think my issue with that is sort of
like
where john seems to be going with this
and of course i can't speak for john but
it seems to me like what john's sort of
saying is
you know a lot of the problems we're
seeing especially around politics are
outgrowths or results of the meeting
crisis
and then if you listen to a lot of
people uh
you know especially some of the the
newer uh outlets that are that are sort
of fighting back against what's called
the establishment
news media in the u.s uh uh so
folks like uh sargon of akkad and tim
poole are two that sort of come to mind
right
uh sargon's in the uk and tim's in the
u.s
um and they're sort of coming to the
fore right their popularity is growing
and one of the themes that they have too
which is kind of weird because it goes
along with john's idea in some sense is
that
politics is downstream of culture right
so
in other words what they're saying is
it's not politics that drove us here and
politics isn't going to drive us
out and so i wanted to get your take on
that because i'm having a
problem from what you're saying figuring
out where you think the prop things need
to be changed because
i think there's no way the evidence is
there's no way in hell that things can
be changed by politics and
and like you know we could go back and
forth on whether or not that's because
the establishment kept bernie sanders
out
or whatnot but that's not relevant if
that's true
it's unfixable and therefore you need to
start somewhere else
and so what do you think of the idea
that politics is actually downstream
from culture and it's kind of like the
end of the chain it's the last thing you
see
after you know it's the last result that
you see and then it'll continue to sort
of catch up
right it's a lagging indicator uh and
and then given that you know where
where do you think given that the you
know if bernie sanders was a real
movement and he could have made it and
he didn't
then that path is cut off so given that
fact
where would you start it can't be
politics where else would you start to
kind of change things yeah
um i think i missed the first part of
what you're saying you're not you
weren't endorsing
sargon or tim poole right you're just
kind of using them as
examples of influential people
look look i mean they're fighting back
against the establishment media
whether that's good or bad i i don't i
don't have a particular opinion
but but the interesting thing to me is
that they're a
fighting back against the establishment
media so that gives them some
credibility in my mind just establishing
meetings
okay so you're a little bit favorable
like you you take you take them
seriously
i mean i'll be blunt i'll be blunt it's
not too
i just we don't have we can unpack it
sometime but i
you know i just want to be blunt i know
that those guys are idiots
and trolls i know that i say that with
full confidence i've seen them
debate i've seen them been taken down i
see the type of videos they
produce yeah no sargon those guys are
controlled i have his t-shirt on this is
a troll
he's racist well i i i don't know about
that he's a troll
he was always a troll
right so so that's not the issue the
issue is
people are seeing the same thing right
which is they both state
in one way or another that politics is
downstream of culture
and and this seems to be a common theme
i mean they're the two
largest audience in that space you have
huge audiences yeah
yeah i'll answer i'll answer your your
question yeah thank you
for the clarification so so i don't
think politics is up or downstream i
i don't i kind of would issue the the
the metaphor i i think
it's a very complex serious question to
grapple with
politics is always happening and
everything's political in some sense
and so we can talk about these issues of
culture and politics
in tandem you know there's a reason
you you know there's degrees in culture
and society and
my expertise is in in politics and
society in fact so political sociology
all these things are connected there's
no upstream no downstream and to frame
it in those types of metaphors
is to uh you know tilt the playing field
and to prioritize different narratives
and you know tim
poole still claims that he's on the left
but you know there's
certain critiques have pointed out that
he's done like you know 17
anti aoc videos in like a week
you know like it's obsessive and
they do have huge platforms it it's
it's a huge problem because
you know he's got confidence he's got
money he just goes online and he talks
and that's part of this
this endemic sort of
you know like it's a broader problem
than just political punditry
you know the whole idea of of gurus
or snake oil salesmen you know going
back to the information ecology question
they they're very bad information
ecologies and if we
if there was a simple answer we would do
it but what i see is a kind of war of
attrition
where they just keep creating more
content and they're winning the click
funnel war over the smaller leftist
channels that regularly debunk them
and it's it's quite a sight to behold if
you actually
have the time but but we're all so
fragmented and pulled in different
directions
you know so i i'm respectful i have to
be
respectful of the the profundity
of the fragmentation of perspectives and
of the of
different people's uh
personal version of the meaning crisis
you know but but um
it's you know so so whatever whatever
tim poole and sargon a cat are tapping
into that might have a nugget of truth
or trump for that matter or jordan
peterson for that matter
or alexander dugan for that matter
they're not the first
people to critique the establishment
they're the last
people they are not even part of that
tradition
they're popping up at our at our
sort of nadir of crisis and saying well
i know what's happening you know
this person sucks this person's good and
it's it's
just degenerating you know further and
further
and i i wish history had forked
differently at so many points in our
recent history because
because it could as i say that's my kind
of my wager
that it could that it could fork and so
so you know
this concept of metanoia is conversion
it's psychological spiritual
and sociological conversion and that's
the type of thing a community like this
will be keen to study and to practice
and to
do these things i'm talking about being
self-critical and self-auditing your
your identity your education your
information ecology because
the experience and the process of
metanoia i think is something we should
aspire to
should aspire you know um you know you
say sargon's not racist he's just a
troll
but if he was aspiring to grok
seriousness of race discourse and of the
experience of minorities and
you know and to relate his own
marginalization
to the marginalization of others as i
have done as a white person
white man this is a positive growth
right become a male feminist in the
basic
sort of popular sense without you know
pissing off too many people
but to advocate for equal rights is a
good thing
people like tim poole and sargon aka
sargon of akkad are not just racist as i
claim they're sexist
too and and then and then it you know
it relates to you know gamergate and in
cell culture and
all these very difficult sociological
problems
and a couple of armchair pundits should
not be leading the cultural conversation
on
but but maybe i could just very well
direct yeah well i i could point out
one thing on that so so for example when
and i'm not trying to be overly
critical but we were talking about how
do we encourage dialogue
um and so so i don't know when you said
you know sargon and timpur are idiots uh
so someone in our one of our audience
members
had typed in chat wow and there's no
point in even being
here and then deleted their post and
then left well there's so so i think
oh i'm sorry i'm sorry if our goal is to
to increase dialogue even if we
like i i have strong criticisms of
sargon and tim poole myself
but but but i i think to
far further dialogue between groups of
divergent views we and i'm i'm trying to
help
yeah you know sir hopefully he'll help
you hear
that you've said you've been cut off by
by other groups that i think that kind
of language
just doesn't help even if even well hold
on a second
yeah i mean it sucks that that happened
but you know this is recorded and on the
record
and maybe we'll track that person down
and
beat him over the head with some good
ideas but but i want to say this
they chose to to leave they chose to
abandon this conversation because they
didn't agree with what i said
anybody can disagree with me but
what's happening is they're having a
cognitive dissonance and they're saying
no [ __ ] this guy
and all i'm saying is you got to be
ready to hear things you don't like
and i know because i've done the
homework that sargon of akkad
is not somebody to look up to or to
listen to
the late great michael brooks is one of
many leftists who did engage sargon of
akkad
go look it up and watch him and and you
know
because it's a spectacle for sargon it
doesn't go well
it does he doesn't get what he wants and
these guys like tim poole and sargon
they're doing they're being rewarded
financially
they are being rewarded financially
that is why they are so stuck in their
ideology
and if i were to debate sorry honor tim
poole
i would really want to have a certain
context i'd want it to be
private let's say we can record it but
let's not make it a spectacle
i'd want it to be mediated i want to
have a
kind of a a panel like an intervention
that these guys aren't interested in
that
and the fact that somebody in this
community john's community
thinks sargon of akkad is worth
listening to boggles my mind
i don't mean to be insensitive and
insulting about i just i'm i'm
showing up to kind of state state what
is provable
and we should all be interested in
hashing that out so i
i think it's just personally that that
uh this is
what i've come up with is that you know
we have these tribal biases
and these these are unconscious and and
and i think
i hear sort of similar things from the
right where where you said
you know people have to be you know
ready to hear things they don't like it
and
and i agree we should be ready that
being said
tribal biases are unconscious and it
takes a tremendous amount of work to get
to the point
where we're not and i don't think we can
even do it entirely
so where we're not influenced by our
tribal biases so
i think this is me personally this it's
not about this conversation about
any conversation between people of
divergent views if we
we have to i or if we want to not
trigger those tribal biases i think we
have to take
efforts not to do that um it it
and and i think that to me my instinct
is that will lead to better results
uh than than just telling people to
to to not take offense or whatnot
um i think it's just the nature of
humans that we're
we are emotional and and and
and it's not about just choosing to be
offended or whatnot we get offended
and maybe through you know deep
meditation practices
and or just developing a thick skin and
i think some people
just naturally have a thicker skin than
others too
but but that if we want to open up
discord my
my primary interest has always been
discourse that i almost don't care
if we come to an agreement if we leave
better understanding one another that is
a great conversation that's a productive
conversation
and if we leave realizing that the other
are not evil that's that's even better
it's about living
and working with each other that we're
always going to have people of divergent
views and that's probably healthy for
society
so how do we do this together you know i
don't want my political personal
political party to win every time i want
the other party to win sometimes because
no no one group
has nailed the has nailed it no one
group has nailed it
so there's pros and cons of both sides
and
and and that's probably very healthy for
society if we ever get stuck in one
track
that will probably lead to bad things as
well you know
i've always thought you know you if when
you aim for utopia
the target is so small that you're
almost guaranteed to miss
and when you miss the results can be
disastrous so
you know the aim isn't necessarily
utopia it's a workable solution
ah um there's a good argument for this
kind of
like incrementalism and of course
treating people with respect you know
and
and and being diplomatic and
um you know
it's ironically again with the idw like
many of their spaces have been the most
hostile to
to dissent and so they they frame
themselves as
the vanguard of of something but
but it's a it's ultimately very
anti-intellectual it's intellectuals
being anti-intellectual and i wrote a
whole
long-form article about that that is a
kind of meta theory that contextualizes
my other critiques knowing how difficult
critique is and how
how difficult it is to change each
other's minds or change our own minds
but there you know
i i respect your process
but i think it doesn't it doesn't scale
fast enough
right and we're we're kind of looking
for solutions like
so when i say politics i don't
mean again that it's you know downstream
or upstream from culture
or that it's or that it's just um a
performance and
the aggregate of different competing
groups is interests
at the at critical moments it's a lever
of change
right so much of what has happened
historically
has including some technological
innovation
has been dependent on on political
change and revolutions aren't always
bloody and so we if we look at
history broadly it contains a lot of
scope for that flexibility and i think
the the cultural
political moment we've been kind of
stuck in for the past 30 years
has been this one that you're describing
of
incremental change but
the the fact is and always has been
that in a certain frame the so-called
democracy in the us
is a kind of false dilemma right that
there's a
two-party oligopoly and so
this is actually a way to transcend that
issue but it doesn't mean the two sides
are equal what it means is
the discourse is already captured so if
you have a political opinion
there's a good chance that you're wrong
and as you said even if you're
a progressive there's there's ways that
can go wrong
right and so i'm i'm also skeptical of
different
uh different uh narratives and different
leaders
when you know somebody like obama he he
kind of very diplomatically commands a
certain
faith and investment in what he's saying
but the the unfortunately the truth is
you know he
was kind of a lame duck and sellout
president in a time when we needed
him to be more radical there's a good
argument for how
obama led to trump
and so by you know
we're in this we're in we're trapped in
this kind of
strange loop you know we're trapped in
this
in in this in this uh time loop just
repeating the same mistakes not wanting
to rock the boat because people are
afraid of
radical change the deeper we get into
the crisis the more obvious
it is that um these the the platform i'm
describing
which is left but could actually be
described as
neutral and universal like a green new
deal unlike
universal healthcare these things are
desperately desperately needed
it's it's virtually a humanitarian
crisis in the united states so it's not
political
in the way people typically think of
politics
as part as an extension of their beliefs
and values
politics in its proper
function to fix these problems and it
requires
a public consciousness it requires a
healthy public discourse
and who's going to help shape the public
discourse if not
the best intellectuals and and their
adherence that we have and again i say
that you know
commentators like tim poole and sargon
avocado are not those people
and and there's you know
members of the intellectual dark web
that have phds and stuff or not
are not those people either and
you know just to to affirm your point
i i'm totally willing to be called out
if i'm not sufficiently diplomatic
you know one of the meanings of me of
metanoia
in the literal in one of the literal
senses like the
uh as a as a linguistic
uh and kind of literature you know
literary maneuver
is to state something
and then take it back and restate it in
a better way
so that's an actual concrete
demonstrable process of metanoia
if i can do that you know then then then
i can take your criticism and you can
help me
reform my message and and
you know that's going to include you
know if
like the guy who took off if i'm able to
see that happening in real time right
which i
which i didn't but if i'm able to see it
then i can kind of go like whoa
hold on a second here like let me let me
try again
let's keep you included in the discourse
because i didn't tell you to [ __ ] off
you know i the more people the better
and the more the more challengers the
better
but you know i also i don't want to
live out the rest of my days just
learning how to be a better debater
we don't have that kind of time we have
about a decade
have a global kind of convergence to
solve climate change
and that's that's that's what matt
that's that's the deepest most real
organizing principle that we should be
you know coupling with this meeting
crisis
no manual you have a question
right so i was listening uh to your talk
with viveke and
you brought up this concept of vicious
abstraction
and that is something to be avoided
and although i'm a little bit iffy on
the definition of
of the thing i can at least see the way
that you used it in relation
to peterson and i was wondering
how you avoid doing vicious abstractions
yourself
yeah thank you that's a great question
and i i recall
from my conversation with raviki that we
we both offered a partial definition
and we kind of we kind of flew by it and
so i appreciate the chance
to revisit that um
i said that vicious abstraction one
example was misquotation
that's a bit limited it's an important
example but
vicious abstraction is also taking
things out of context
so like
the idea of misquotation like if you
take a
quote of somebody from speech or from a
book
and use that to make a bad faith
critique of them
and say well this is what they said you
know and then that other that person has
to come back and say well that's not
what i said you know you took it out of
context
that's a vicious abstraction and that's
a that's a fallacy
right the person who did that made a
mistake
in in misquoting and so you know as a
from a scholarship point of view
obviously you're trained not to do that
you're trained to
take sources very seriously to to not
plagiarize
to think critically to
um evaluate claims and to represent them
authentically and it's
it's it's difficult to do i think you
know
casually and unconsciously we all do
vicious abstractions
by be unintentionally misinterpreting
something
and then say oh you know so-and-so said
this and it so gets passed on
like the telephone game
but we also do it in a in a conscious
way i think that can be
intervened on more if you're aware of it
and so
i think yeah yeah
so i just want to introduce the way that
i think about these things right
because sure we always need to relate to
something in a context right so whenever
we're relating to a thing we're
always establishing a context from which
we're relating to the thing that's
necessary
right and other people will necessarily
disagree with that
context because we have different
perspectives so
i don't think we can avoid vicious
abstractions
in in that sense and i i think that the
only
thing we can do is be graceful towards
people when we do it and then we can
adjust
our perspectives but um i'm
yeah like when
when you suppose that that can be
fixed like like i'm really skeptical
when i hear that so i i'd like to get
sure a little bit into that like how do
you perfect i appreciate the question
so i was trying to give an example of
vicious abstraction but that's not all
it is it's not just and so i can give an
another example
if we're trying to define concept of of
a chair
or a car you know or a horse like that
is an abstraction
right we we can create an ideal form of
it to say
you know a horse has short thick
hair it has four legs it has a um
you know a a kind of
like a mane and you know a long face
that's a horse and then
you know and then i would you know i say
it's either brown or black and then
or white and then you you know you say
well what about a zebra
like these are there's a different
abstractions right like what are the
requirements of the thing
to qualify as the abstraction like does
a chair
have to have legs or can it sit on the
floor and still be a chair like these
are really banal examples
the point i'm trying to get to when we
talk about
higher level con you know abstractions
like
liberalism democracy capitalism
neoliberalism
marxism these are containers
which actually contain a lot of other
ideas
and so there's a concept of leaky
abstractions
i'm not sure if i'm actually agreeing
with that like
why can't they be containers that are
big ideas that don't contain small ideas
like
i don't see it's necessary that that
they have to contain those ideas
um i'm not sure the critique you're
making i'm not saying it like
like a certain definition might contain
a minimum
set of characteristics
right so so a proper definition
of something like marxism or fascism
will have a generally agreed upon
set of features to it and so let's call
them like
points in or something like a bullet
point so
does it have five features does it have
10 does it have
i think you know we that's something we
would explore but
but like we can agree that the word
essence right like something has an
essence right something is identified by
its essence
yeah we're talking about abstractions
very high level abstractions
that's irrelevant the abstraction of a
horse
abstraction of a horse directly
correlates to the to an actual horse
the abstraction of capitalism has
many layers of correlation with many
other ideas these are macro concepts
and so my point with vicious abstraction
if if somebody mischaracterizes what
capitalism
actually is in the abstract
that's a vicious abstraction and it's
called vicious because it has
vicious knock-on effects and so the goal
between us should be the clarity of the
of the abstractions and the good good
faith transmission of those ideas
i'm confused why can't there be an
essence of capitalism
um the short answer is because it's it's
socially constructed and it evolves over
time
capitalism is something that we made up
and that we that we
determine but that doesn't mean the
definition is totally relativists
like that there's your capitalism in my
capitalism
what it is as an abstraction is
something that correlates to
many concrete realities
right like the concept of money the the
concept of
of st of exchange of interest of
property ownership
right there's all these features and a
vicious abstraction is when certain of
those
aspects get purposefully or or
accidentally left out
so let me let me try to suggest an
alternative for you
to to relate to this right so so i
and i'm gonna go to platonic forms here
right so we we have an
ascent right we have an essential
structure right something that's
necessarily true for the thing to exist
right and then we have
implementation of the essential
structure in reality right
and those are two different things right
we can distinguish between
the essential structure and how we are
using it and like
i i think when you're saying well
there's all of these nuances
the nuances are in the use of the thing
not in the thing itself
i think i think if we use language and
we use definition
right like the definition is pointing at
a thing and we can talk about the thing
without its implementation
yeah you're talking about like the idea
of a house behind all houses right
and i i don't see what the contradiction
was directly with what i was trying to
say because i'm trying to say there's an
idea of a horse there's an idea of a car
that is behind all the instances there's
also an idea of capitalism
that is not contingent upon all the
aspects that you
put onto it right like you can put them
on later right and then we have
an american implementation of capitalism
when you have a european
implementation of capitalism not
contradictory with
capitalism as essential
structure and then the essential
structure well the point i'm trying to
make is
that the essential structure thereby
cannot be viciously abstracted because
it's essential right like
there is no negative interpretation of
the thing it's just defined as a thing
right but it still hinges on the
definition like where is it defined
point to the definition that is the
abstraction ultimately that we have to
to cope with and i'm saying if people
misrepresent
that form it's a vicious abstraction
i'm trying to agree with you that
somewhere out there there's an ideal of
capitalism
but the vicious misrepresent the
misrepresentation
of it is a vicious abstraction the only
way to counter that
whether in dialogue or as a personal
investigation to research the definition
right so you know i've i've lost count
to the number of times people tell me
that
neoliberalism doesn't mean anything of
course it means something it's just very
far removed from daily discourse and
from
you know it's very distorted through
different narratives
but i would hope we can agree on that
neoliberalism is a subset
of capitalism it means different things
to different people
that that that differentiated meaning
is viciously distorted in different uh
for different different audiences
i think there if there is a a true
meaning it's very hard to reach
because abstractions are inherently
out of reach they're they're they're
mental
projections that that people came up
with and mediated through
through the process of
of you know academia and debate and and
so we're still
grappling with um unfolding those things
right it's not
like the end of the cold war was a clear
victory for capitalism and a
failure it was certainly a failure of
communism but not necessarily a failure
of the idea of socialism because
inequality and
and stuff has increased since then and
the climate catastrophe has deepened
since then so part of the meaning crisis
i think to put it in those terms
is the the failure to
really grok these abstractions like
capitalism and and
climate change you know so we end up
having endless debates over them but
people are talking past each other
because they don't mean this
the same thing if we had a third party
mediator
said hey this is what capitalism is this
definition i'm going to read
is sort of co-developed by you know
scholars and kind of
match with a general understanding and
this is what some of the stuff people
typically get wrong about it
you know i think i think that's key to
having any kind of
constructive debate so
this is what i mean by vicious
abstraction you know it has many
meanings but the key is to understand
what good abstraction is in the first
place
well okay so um
i would argue with the fact that it's an
abstraction
like when when you're talking about
something that's
an essence right like you cannot like
you need to abstract something from the
essence or something
in order for it to be an abstraction and
if it's just a thing it's just a thing
so i don't
and and i agree with you yeah
a lot of people who are using terms
right like and
and they're abstracting things from
systems
all the time and like i i i really
really dislike it like i'm i'm totally
on board with you on that
that that part so so like like
i like that but the idea that that that
is a problem but like
yeah like i i just get the feeling when
i'm talking to you that you're you're
taking it like
one step too far and like it's the issue
the issue is is in in the
the not being careful with speech as
opposed to
uh the abstractions or whatever like
like i don't
the abstractions are just manifestations
of us
not having our thoughts in order and not
having
well-reasoned arguments basically
yeah i yeah i think we have some common
ground here i think it's a very complex
question though you know abstraction is
kind of my
wheelhouse that i've carved out for
myself and it's a big part of
what i'm trying to demonstrate about the
sociology of knowledge
that we all are operating with different
different abstractions like every word
is an abstraction
the more abstract that word is the more
uh prone it likely is to
misinterpretation or
or distortion and so i think that at
that
prompts a lot of confusion and and
um divergences of opinions and
you know to just a sort of case in point
with capitalism is the way jordan
peterson talks about capitalism and
marxism
in my writings i use him as an example
of committing vicious abstraction
because he's not using the terms in any
way
is legible or compatible with
actual experts on on capitalism or
critics of capitalism like
or or economist you know peterson's
essentially taking a reductionist view
right and that's what i'm saying is
vicious abstraction when you collapse
capitalism and say
in into market fundamentalism basically
the idea of market fundamentalism is you
equate
free markets with being the generator of
freedom
and as the unimpeachable basis of
capitalism
having free markets is just part of the
big picture and market fundamentalists
are often
just quite ideological and quite opposed
to
debate you know they're they're the ones
funding the denial think tanks right
this is just this is what is kind of
laid out in the literature so just one
second brent i just wanted to be
respectful of your time we're at about
the 90 minute mark uh
i'm happy to keep this going as long as
you are but i just wanted to
i didn't know if you had any time
commitments uh
thanks um i would like to keep going if
if you guys are into it because there's
we've got
you know close to a dozen people in the
chat and i'm
appreciating the engagement so
happy to keep going if if we all have
the stamina for it absolutely
yeah so sorry sorry to interrupt daniel
uh keep on going
well yeah i'm
like so i'm gonna get back onto my hobby
horse here
there is from my perspective right like
all all the people right like when you
have an idea
right you can detach
the idea from a school like i feel like
too many people like and and this is a
critique i have a view with the
post-modernism right like i think
post-modernism was a reaction to what
happened in the second world war
right and then there was a group
of thinkers right and that group of
thinkers grew and grew and grew and grew
but like
to put that all right like either you
choose the fact that
where where the thing originated as as
what post-modernism is or you
you choose to to whatever
is now happening as as as the label post
modernism but
but if you use what's now as as the
label like that that doesn't seem to
make sense at least from my perspective
because in in a sense it's
meaningless right like the meaning of
post-modernism comes from its
historical context right so so then i'm
like well
maybe these people from my perspective
are not post-modern thinkers at least if
their ideas are not
related to the post-modern critique
right and and this is yeah
let me post modernism is a good example
let me just pivot
to the concept of a leaky abstraction
um it comes from computer science but i
you know i think it applies to two words
too like conceptually postmodernism is
messy
i'm not like don't identify as a
postmodernist or anything that's why i
write about
modernism as a different thing and that
is a
complex topic too right it's still
evolving it's still
disputed and my article was largely
about that the kind of historiography
of that so it's a it's a complex
overview of that
and i have a whole section on
post-modernism and the point is
it's very difficult to reduce
post-modernism to a single universal
definition
that doesn't mean it's wrong it means
the term itself
is is a is a kind of um
slippery or diaphanous container for a
cert for a bunch of ideas but one of my
key points is that it's irreducible and
if people reduce it to say hey
post-modernism is
this post-modernism is relativism
that's a vicious abstraction that does a
disservice to
ourselves as thinkers because these
things are more complex i'm
i'm going the opposite way i'm i'm
you're saying there's an essence to all
these words
you're kind of well there needs to be
well not not i'm not trying to be a
realist i'm
trying to be a pragmatist and i'm like
if if i want to use a word
right it needs to mean a thing and if it
doesn't mean a thing it's not a word
right it's just
jumbo jumbo so so either it is
translated right
in you know johnny converse or sorry not
uh not rather
uh john well john vervicky is versed in
the classics and all that but those
things are translated from greek in
translation
things get mistranslated metanoia is a
case in point
because the bible translated metanoia
from its original meaning of change of
mind
to repentance this is a classic example
of what what i'm talking about of
vicious abstraction i'm not saying it's
intentional i'm not saying the effects
are necessarily
that damaging or vicious but it is a
misrepresentation or
miscommunication of the original intent
i
you know i'm not a linguist but a basis
of linguistics
is how a lot of it is metaphysical and
socially constructed
don't agree that words have an essence
um
and i think we we could defer to john or
to
whoever you know on on that topic maybe
maybe you and i are just
talking past each other and that's the
last thing i want oh no
well okay i i want your argument right
so if words don't have an
essence what are we doing like they have
the essences
they have essences i mean i'm trying to
meet you halfway
and say that they they have enough
meaning for us to be able to communicate
but not everybody has the same sort of
education or
or primary language growing up maybe
english is their second life
i'm not arguing that that is true right
like that's a straw man of my position
i'm not arguing that everybody
looks at the words the same way right
that that's
definitely not what i'm doing right like
what i'm arguing is that there's a
platonic form
right that is being
symbolized by the word and
we all have different conceptualizations
of the platonic form because of our
historical
uh upbringing but but that doesn't mean
that the form isn't there and that we're
not talking about the same thing right
so if if you're saying the form isn't
there then
then then i like i don't have to
communicate with you anymore because i'm
not talking about the same thing anyway
and if you say the form is there that
means that every word
is pointing at that form so so then
we're gonna have to need a form for
every word like like i don't see a
middle ground there
um yeah i mean this is a very
philosophical
kind of point and debate
you know are the forms there are the
forms not there
part of my approach would be to say like
you know it's important to learn that
stuff
but that it's also
it's very speculative if it's neither
here nor there you know the
the forms are here the forms are there
wherever
like i'm definitely getting lost on one
end of this
conversation about about forms but like
i like the idea of forms like
you can't have forms without abstraction
right the the key i'm trying to
emphasize here is not plato
it's the process of abstraction itself
the process of thinking that we all do
has to be
understood in a way beyond plato
so so i think right like okay so so i'm
gonna
invert it right so i think if you take
the form
as primary right then we necessarily
when we have a word we have an
abstraction of the form
right we cannot hold the whole constants
on our minds because that's too big and
we have limited life experience
right so we always gain an abstraction
right
but as long as we hold in our minds that
what we're relating to is an abstraction
of something that's beyond
the word then we're good
right but that that needs a sense of
humility right
so so for example right like when you
when you went to your translation of the
metanoia
into what was it uh repentance
repentance like i was i was okay with
that i like i didn't
think that was a mistranslation at all
so from my conceptualization
and my understanding of christianity
that that is a good
and a good good representation of that
concept so
like that's precisely what i'm getting
at though
is is if you read what the scholars are
saying about the translation
in part i'm just echoing what the
scholars have said they're describing it
as a definite mistranslation right so
i'm not saying it doesn't make sense
repentance does make sense in the
context
but it's not the complete translation
according to these scholars right these
are biblical
scholars and historians philosophers
who are saying that it's mistranslated
and not only are they saying that
there's for example the book that i
recommend to john
in our previous talk that's unreleased
it's called metanoia it's by bloomsbury
and it's it it's developing this concept
from a cognitive
uh a cognitive theory point of view it's
it's developing the concept of metanoia
from john's discipline
and so that is an authority on the
concept that is obviously beyond the
bible
but the bible the biblical scholars are
still
you know accessing some deep historical
resonance with the concept and and both
are interesting to me
so metanoia is an abstraction good luck
to finding the form i mean that's what
i'm saying is we can write and talk
about these things till the cows come
home
and they're they're you you're never
gonna
draw the shape of it it you know
so so a lot of these discourses like
forms
just help us get to a certain point like
plato's cave is allegorical
you know
so i'm i'm with you that we're never
going to draw the shape
but that doesn't mean that we can't
relate to it and and like
yeah we we have to try we we we have to
try
we don't have to try we do we do it all
the time and
and that works fine and like i don't see
a problem with it the problem is vicious
abstraction the problem is when
it doesn't go fine and people could do
it intentionally right because they have
malicious interests or they could do it
unconsciously because they're
a a useful idiot to use the term in a
neutral way like
you know like so what i'm saying is
is communication is not always pure far
from it whether we're talking about
ordinary people or philosophers i think
vicious abstraction
happens quite commonly it's quite it's
quite
it happens frequently and it's common
it's bad it's bad it it increases the
noise in the signal
so my my whole thesis there is just that
vicious abstraction is
is bad that's what william james says
about it
that's what i wrote about it in the
context of
of racism because there was a kind of
the historical abstraction of race
discourse
from like uh you know slurs
to coded language like redlining
or forced busing or states rights states
rights
were actually ways to make more abstract
the
the values of racism which um
republican voters in the in the
uh 60s and this you know according to
the southern strategy
in the 60s and 70s it's um
appealed to voters it was was coded
racism so
those that was a kind of vicious
abstraction because they're mis they're
they're mis
not in now this isn't an example of
mistranslation
misquotation but it's another example of
vicious abstraction which is
using different coded language right
that's dehumanization
right so first first i was tracking your
your description of fish's abstraction
as idolatry
right um as misquotation
as a kind of false representation
and taken out of context um idolatry can
be part of it
right so under this one is is
dehumanization
right so where you where you uh
drag the human out of the context and
and
and make it a more objective
language where where where it doesn't
relate to to the individual anymore
but yeah like i think
i'm gonna see the floor but those those
things have been
talked about since i appreciate the
chance to
try to unpack both abstraction and
vicious abstraction
well thank you that that was great uh
i really appreciate you staying staying
a bit later that was really interesting
discussion there were so many topics
actually i wanted to get into that we
didn't get into so we're definitely
gonna have to have you
have you back brent and and probably a
good time to do that would be after your
next uh
after your next uh voices with for reiki
that i guess will be
the upcoming sure sure i i
i appreciate the the the feedback as i
said to you offline before we started i
don't even remember half the things john
and i talked about
so it's nice to have a refresher
and um if you wanted to close out the
hour if there's any final questions i'm
i'm happy to do so
i think we i think well other questions
i'd have would probably take would
probably take us into
probably take us well beyond well beyond
uh so
yeah and i think we're we we've gone
through the questions that were there
but this was just
fascinating i i really enjoyed this
conversation
really happy that you came on and thank
you so much for being here
and uh thanks for everyone for being
here and asking some great questions and
just joining us in this queue i like i
like being in the hot seat
and um thanks for everyone's patience
and uh i'll i'll see you next time
yeah thank you so much so so thank you
brent
cooper for being here uh i i put the
link to his voices with raviki
and uh his website is www.abs.tract.org
and so definitely check him out and
uh and watch the voices with for vicky
if you if you haven't yet so thank you
thank you again
and we'll be back next time with more
guests so
stay tuned have a great day everyone
yeah thanks brent appreciate it
cheers thank you yeah thanks